Finding Aid for the Peace Corps Collection
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Peace Corps Collection
multiple
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0328
5 linear_feet
Biographical Sketch
Nicholas Hobbs was born March 13, 1915 in Greenville, South Carolina. He earned an A.B. at The Citadel in 1936, an M.A. at Ohio State University in 1938, and at the same institution, a Ph. D in 1946. From 1941 to 1946 he served in the United States Army Air Force, and in 1949 he married Mary M. Thompson. The couple had one son, Nicholas Thompson Hobbs. Dr. Hobbs taught at Riverside Military Academy (1936-1937) and Spartanburg High School (1937–1938) before beginning his college teaching career at Columbia Teachers College and later Louisiana State University.
Dr. Hobbs joined the faculty of George Peabody College for Teachers in 1951. He was especially interested in the lives of children and was a leader in the development over 20 years of Project Re-ED, a program for emotionally disturbed children. He documented this work in his book The Troubled and Troubling Child. In 1961, in addition to his faculty responsibilities, he accepted the position of Director of Recruitment, and then in 1962, Director of Research for the Peace Corps. He established the Kennedy Center for the Study of Families and Children at the Vanderbilt Institute for Public Policy Studies. Between 1967 and 1975 he was a Provost of Vanderbilt University. During his career, he also served as President of the Southeastern Psychological Association and the American Psychological Association, receiving from the latter group two awards for distinguished contributions to public service.
Nicholas Hobbs died on January 23, 1983, and on January 30 a Celebration of the Life of Nicholas Hobbs was held at the Benton Chapel on the Vanderbilt campus.
Scope and Content Note
In 1961 Dr. Nicholas Hobbs, Professor of Psychology at George Peabody College for Teachers, was appointed as the Director of Recruitment and in 1962 as the Director of Research for the Peace Corps. This collection consists of the correspondence these positions required as well as the materials related to the collaborative efforts of Dr. Hobbs and colleagues around the country to develop test materials and evaluation techniques in order to recruit, select, and retain the best candidates for the Peace Corps. As these materials reveal, candidates were subjected to extensive testing and evaluation before selection. After selection the Peace Corps volunteers continued to be evaluated while serving in their assignments around the world. Various types of carefully researched and developed testing materials are in the collection, most notably Dr. Hobbs’s Overseas Experience Battery (Inventory).
Also included are materials on the Peace Corps projects in 35 countries, ranging from Afghanistan to Venezuela. The two boxes of correspondence include many letters from Sergent Shriver, Director of the Peace Corps. Because this was a federal government program, there are also numerous forms concerning guidelines, such as how to request funding or how to submit research proposals
- Correspondence---Incoming---Adams-Ashcroft (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence---Incoming---Backe-Bunger (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence---Incoming---Calvert-Cauthen (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence--- Incoming---Charters-Colmen (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence--- Incoming---Colmen-David (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence---Incoming---Davis-Erlandson (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence---Incoming---Evans-Flack (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence---Incoming---Flanagan-Freedman (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence---Incoming---Fuchs-Gollin (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence---Incoming---Graham-Hedges (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence---Incoming---Hedges-Jouard (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Correspondence---Incoming---Julian-Krug (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Correspondence---Incoming---Layton-Melton (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence---Incoming---Menninger-Osgood (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence---Incoming-Paar-Pratt (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Correspondence---Incoming-Poznak-Ryans (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence---Incoming---Scanlon-Shriver (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence---Incoming---Shriver-Tilley (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Correspondence---Incoming---Vaughn-Zack (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Correspondence----Outgoing, February 27, 1961-December 29, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Correspondence---Outgoing, January 2, 1962-March 13, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Correspondence---Outgoing, March 14, 1962-May 29, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Correspondence---Outgoing, May 31, 1962-August 17, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Correspondence---Outgoing, September 10, 1962-November 5, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Correspondence---Outgoing, November 13, 1962-December 31, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Correspondence---Outgoing, January 2, 1963-March 29, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Correspondence---Outgoing, April 2, 1963-December 30, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Correspondence---Outgoing, January 3, 1964-August 8, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Correspondence---Government Regulations re Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Correspondence---Government Regulations re Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Peace Corps---Staff Meetings (Directors), 1961-1964 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Peace Corps---Prospective Personnel (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Peace Corps---Staff Directories and Personnel Lists, 1961-1964 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Peace Corps---Program Projections and Plans (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Peace Corps---News Articles and Releases, 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Peace Corps---News Articles and Releases, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Peace Corps---News Articles and Releases, 1963-1964 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Peace Corps---Publicity Pamphlets (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Peace Corps---The Peace Corps Volunteer-Statistical Summary, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Peace Corps---The Peace Corps Volunteer-Statistical Summary, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Peace Corps---The Peace Corps Volunteer-Statistical Summary, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Peace Corps---Requirements for Peace Corps Personnel Overseas (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Peace Corps---Peace Corps Applicant Questionnaire (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Peace Corps---Volunteer Handbook (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Peace Corps---Volunteer Self-Evaluation Inventory (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Peace Corps---Follow-Up Studies of Returned Volunteers (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Peace Corps---Public Addresses on the Peace Corps by Dr. Nicholas Hobbs (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Peace Corps---Public Addresses on the Peace Corps by Others (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Peace Corps---Volunteer Selection Process (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Peace Corps---Review of Volunteer Selection Process (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Peace Corps---Personal Audit and Self-Selection Questions for Volunteers (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Peace Corps---Research---General (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Peace Corps---Research Conference, March 4-5, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Peace Corps---Research Operations of the Peace Corps (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Peace Corps---Guide for the Preparation of Research Proposals for the Peace Corps (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Peace Corps---Research Notes (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Peace Corps---Presentation to the United States Congress, January 29, 1962-First Draft (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Peace Corps---Peace Corps Congressional Presentation, Vol. I, FY, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Peace Corps---Peace Corps Congressional Presentation, Vol. II, FY, 1964; (2 copies) (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Peace Corps---Peace Corps Congressional Presentation, Vol. III, FY, 1964; (2 copies) (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Peace Corps---Book Coordination Office (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Peace Corps---Medical Exam Instruction Sheet and Immunization Information (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Peace Corps---Memoranda for Peace Corps Representatives and Staff (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Peace Corps---National Service Corps (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Peace Corps---Youth Conservation Corps (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Peace Corps---Budget and Finances (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Peace Corps---Graduate Nurses in Peace Corps Health Projects (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Peace Corps---Career Information Service for Returning Peace Corps Volunteers (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Peace Corps---Proposed Peabody Peace Corps Training Program (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Peace Corps---Status Report on Peace Corps Projects, 1962-1964 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Peace Corps---Projects---Afghanistan (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Peace Corps---Projects---Bolivia (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Peace Corps---Projects---Brazil (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Peace Corps---Projects---Ceylon (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Peace Corps---Projects---Chile (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Peace Corps---Projects---Colombia (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Peace Corps---Projects---Colombia (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Peace Corps---Projects----Colombia (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Peace Corps---Projects---Colombia (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Peace Corps---Projects---Colombia (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Peace Corps---Projects---Colombia (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Peace Corps---Projects---Costa Rica (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Peace Corps---Projects---Cyprus (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Peace Corps---Projects---Dominican Republic (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Peace Corps---Projects---Ecuador (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Peace Corps---Projects---El Salvador (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Peace Corps---Projects---Ethiopia (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Peace Corps---Projects---Ghana (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Peace Corps---Projects---Ghana (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Peace Corps---Projects---Ghana (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Peace Corps---Projects---Ghana (Box 7, Folder 13)
- Peace Corps---Projects---Ghana (Box 7, Folder 14)
- Peace Corps---Projects---Ghana (Box 7, Folder 15)
- Peace Corps---Projects---Guatemala (Box 7, Folder 16)
- Peace Corps---Projects---Honduras (Box 7, Folder 17)
- Peace Corps---Projects---India (Box 7, Folder 18)
- Peace Corps---Projects---Iran (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Peace Corps---Projects---Ivory Coast (West Africa) (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Peace Corps---Projects---Jamaica (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Peace Corps---Projects–Liberia (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Peace Corps---Projects---Malaya (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Peace Corps---Projects---Nepal (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Peace Corps---Projects---Nigeria (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Peace Corps---Projects---Nigeria (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Peace Corps---Projects---Nigeria (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Peace Corps---Projects---North Borneo (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Peace Corps---Projects---Pakistan (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Peace Corps---Projects---Peru (Box 8, Folder 12)
- Peace Corps-Projects---Philippines (Box 8, Folder 13)
- Peace Corps---Projects---Philippines (Box 8, Folder 14)
- Peace Corps--- Projects---Philippines (Box 8, Folder 15)
- Peace Corps---Projects---Puerto Rico (Box 8, Folder 16)
- Peace Corps---Projects---Sierra Leone (Box 8, Folder 17)
- Peace Corps---Projects–Tanganyika (Box 8, Folder 18)
- Peace Corps-Projects---Tanganyika (Box 8, Folder 19)
- Peace Corps Projects---Tanganyika (Box 8, Folder 20)
- Peace Corps---Projects---Thailand (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Peace Corps---Projects---Togo (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Peace Corps---Projects---Tunisia (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Peace Corps---Projects---Turkey (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Peace Corps---Projects---Venezuela (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Peace Corps---Research---Questionnaire for Volunteers (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Peace Crops---Research---Report of the Final Selection Board (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Peace Corps---Research---Entrance Tests (Box 9, Folder 8)
- Peace Corps---Research---Entrance Test, Part 1 (Box 9, Folder 9)
- Peace Corps---Research---Entrance Tests (5 booklets) (Box 9, Folder 10)
- Peace Corps---Research---Statistical Summary of Entrance Tests (Box 9, Folder 11)
- Peace Corps---Research---Instructions to Evaluators (Box 9, Folder 12)
- Peace Corps---Research---Validation Studies of the Selection Process (Box 9, Folder 13)
- Peace Corps---Research---Characteristics of Volunteers Assigned in 1961 (Box 9, Folder 14)
- Peace Corps---Research---Working Effectively Overseas (Box 9, Folder 15)
- Peace Corps---Research---Instructional Situations (Box 9, Folder 16)
- Peace Corps---Research–Hobbs Rating Scale for Overseas Performance (Box 9, Folder 17)
- Peace Corps---Research---Completed Rating Scales---Ghana (Box 9, Folder 18)
- Peace Corps----Research---Completed Rating Scales---Philippines (Box 9, Folder 19)
- Peace Corps---Research---Completed Rating Scales–Pakistan (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Peace Corps---Research---Completed Rating Scales---Tanganyika (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Peace Corps---Research---College Characteristics Index (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Peace Corps---Research---Personality Change Battery (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Peace Corps---Research---Personality Change Battery (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Peace Corps---Research---Personality Change Battery (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Peace Corps---Research---Personality Change Battery (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Peace Corps---Research---Personality Change Battery (Box 10, Folder 8)
- Peace Corps---Research---Evaluation of Field Service Abroad through Reports of Participants (Box 10, Folder 9)
- Peace Corps---Research---Hobbs Peace Corps Overseas Experience Battery (Box 10, Folder 10)
- Peace Corps---Research---Hobbs Peace Corps Overseas Experience Battery (Box 10, Folder 11)
- Peace Corps---Research---Research---Hobbs Peace Corps Experience Battery (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Peace Corps---Research---Project Talent (Box 11, Folder 2)
- Peace Corps---Research---Hobbs Overseas Experience Battery for Missionaries (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Peace Corps---Research---Analysis of Motivations for Applying to the Peace Corps (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Peace Corps---Research---Data Storage Needs (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Peace Corps---Research---Public Information Form by Hobbs (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Peace Corps---Research---Critical Incidence Forms (Box 11, Folder 7)
- Peace Corps---Research---Questionnaire for Predicting the Success of the Peace Corps (Box 11, Folder 8)
- Peace Corps---Research---Predicting the Success of the Peace Corps Volunteers in Nigeria (Box 11, Folder 9)
- Peace Corps---Research---Predicting the Success of Peace Corps Volunteers in Peru and Malaya (Box 11, Folder 10)
- Peace Corps---Research---Training Grades and Test Scores Form (Box 11, Folder 11)
- Peace Corps---Research---Booklet-Why People Join the Peace Corps (Box 11, Folder 12)
- Peace Corps---Research---Studies on Comparative Psycholinguistics (Box 11, Folder 13)
- Peace Corps---Research---Semantic Differential Study (Box 11, Folder 14)
- Peace Corps---Research---The Cross-Cultural Generality of Meaning Systems (Box 11, Folder 15)
- Peace Corps---Research---Miscellaneous Writings by Paar, Pressey, and the United States Department of Health, Education and Welfare (Box 11, Folder 16)
- Peace Corps---Research---End of Service Conference and Test Materials (Box 11, Folder 17)
  The files in Boxes 12, 13, and 14 contain index cards with the responses to Overseas Experience Inventory, Book 3---Incomplete Sentences. See Box 10, File 10 for the Inventory.
- Peace Corps---Research---Responses, Book 3 (Box 12, Folder 1)
- Peace Corps---Research---Responses, Book 3, Set 2 (Box 12, Folder 2)
- Peace Corps---Research---Responses, Book 3, Set 3 (Box 12, Folder 3)
- Peace Corps---Research---Responses, Book 3, Set 7 (Box 12, Folder 4)
- Peace Corps---Research---Responses, Book 3, Set 8 (Box 12, Folder 5)
- Peace Corps---Research---Responses, Book 3, Set 9 (Box 12, Folder 6)
- Peace Corps---Research---Responses, Book 3, Set 10 (Box 12, Folder 7)
- Peace Corps---Research---Responses, Book 3. Set 11 (Box 12, Folder 8)
- Peace Corps---Research---Responses, Book 3, Set 12 (Box 12, Folder 9)
- Peace Corps---Research---Responses, Book 3, Set 13 (Box 12, Folder 10)
- Peace Corps---Research---Responses, Book 3, Set 14 (Box 12, Folder 11)
- Peace Corps---Research---Responses, Book 3, Set 15 (Box 13, Folder 1)
- Peace Corps---Research---Responses, Book 3, Set 16 (Box 13, Folder 2)
- Peace Corps---research---Responses, Book 3, Set 17 (Box 13, Folder 3)
- Peace Corps---Research---Responses, Book 3, Set 18 (Box 13, Folder 4)
- Peace Corps---Research---Responses, Book 3, Set 19 (Box 13, Folder 5)
- Peace Corps---Research---Responses, Book 3, Set 20 (Box 13, Folder 6)
- Peace Corps---Research---Responses, Book 3, Set 21 (Box 13, Folder 7)
- Peace Corps---Research---Responses, Book 3, Set 22 (Box 13, Folder 8)
- Peace Corps---Research---Responses, Book 3, Set 23 (Box 13, Folder 9)
- Peace Corps---Research, Responses, Book 3, Set 24 (Box 13, Folder 10)
- Peace Corps---Research---Responses, Book 3, Set 25 (Box 14, Folder 1)
- Peace Corps---Research---Responses, Book 3, Set 26 (Box 14, Folder 2)
- Peace Corps---Research---Responses, Book 3, Set 27 (Box 14, Folder 3)
- Peace Corps---Research---Responses, Book 3, Set 28 (Box 14, Folder 4)
- Peace Corps---Research---Responses, Book 3, Set 29 (Box 14, Folder 5)
- Peace Corps---Research---responses, Book 3, Set 30 (Box 14, Folder 6)